Guide to the Mark Holloway Papers Related to Martha Gordon Crotch
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Mark Holloway papers related to Martha Gordon Crotch
1890-1970
1935-1970
GEN MSS 933
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5
(5 boxes)
The papers consist of material gathered by Mark Holloway in preparation for his unpublished biography of Martha Gordon Crotch. Series I holds Crotch's autograph manuscript diaries describing her daily activities between 1935 and 1956 and her relationships with friends Alexander (Sasha) Berkman, Emmy Eckstein, Emma Goldman, Frieda Lawrence, and Norman Douglas, among others. Also present is a typescript of Crotch's autobiography, some personal papers, and photographs, including a folder of material on Francis Frederick Gordon, editor of the Advocate of India. Series II holds Mark Holloway's notes and other research material, as well as autograph manuscript and typescript pages of outlines, drafts, and chapters of his projected book which had the working title "Auntie: a biographical memoir of Mrs. Gordon Crotch (1879-1967) of Vence, and of some of her friends -- Frieda Lawrence, Emma Goldman, Norman Douglas, and Robert Nichols -- during the decade 1930-1940."
Holloway, Mark, 1917-2004
Crotch, Martha Gordon
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2004.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Mark Holloway (1917-2004)
Mark Holloway, English poet, editor, and biographer.
Martha Gordon Crotch (1879-1967)
Martha Harriet Gordon was born in Hartlepool, England; she became officially, by deed poll in 1929, Martha Gordon Crotch, presumably due to an association with her friend William Walter Crotch. Known as "Auntie," she was the proprietor of The Peasant Shop, a bohemian pottery store/antiques shop/tea room in the artists' colony in Vence, France.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of material gathered by Mark Holloway in preparation for his unpublished biography of Martha Gordon Crotch. Series I holds Crotch's autograph manuscript diaries describing her daily activities between 1935 and 1956 and her relationships with friends Alexander (Sasha) Berkman, Emmy Eckstein, Emma Goldman, Frieda Lawrence, and Norman Douglas, among others. Also present is the typescript of Crotch's autobiography and some personal papers and photographs, including a folder of material on Francis Frederick Gordon, editor of the Advocate of India. Series II holds Mark Holloway's notes and other research material, as well as autograph manuscript and typescript pages of outlines, drafts, and chapters of his projected book, which had the working title "Auntie: a biographical memoir of Mrs. Gordon Crotch (1879-1967) of Vence, and of some of her friends -- Frieda Lawrence, Emma Goldman, Norman Douglas, and Robert Nichols -- during the decade 1930-1940."
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Martha Gordon Crotch Papers, 1890-1970. II. Mark Holloway Papers, undated.
Authors, English -- 20th Century; Vence (France); Diaries -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; Photographs -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; Authors -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Crotch, Martha Gordon; Douglas, Norman, 1868-1952; Eckstein, Emmy, 1900-1939; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Gordon, Francis Frederick, -1922; Holloway, Mark, 1917-2004; Lawrence, D. H. (David Herbert), 1885-1930; Lawrence, Frieda, 1879-1956; Nichols, Robert, 1893-1944
- Martha Gordon Crotch Papers, 1890-1970; Series I; 2; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into two subseries: Personal Papers, and Writings.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains papers obtained by Holloway and used as reference sources while preparing his biography of Crotch. Aside from her autograph manuscript diaries, and her autobiography, also present is a folder of material on Francis Frederick Gordon, editor of the Advocate of India, a newspaper published in Bombay, India, from 1887 to 1925.
  - Personal Papers
    - Diaries, 1935-1956, undated; 35 (Box 1)
    - Passport and other papers, 1920, 1956 (Box 2)
    - Photographs, circa 1890-circa 1970 (Box 2)
      General note
      Includes copy photographs and negatives made for Mark Holloway
    - Printed ephemera, 1931, undated (Box 2)
      Includes palm cards announcing D. H. Lawrence's painting exhibition at the Peasant Shop, April 6, 1931, and a business card for the shop, among other things.
    - Francis Frederick Gordon, 1922-1923 (Box 2)
      Contains an obituary, probate papers, and an inventory of the contents of the Advocate of India press plant.
    - Letters, 1933-1962 (Box 2)
  - Writings
    - Transcript of autobiography, undated; 3 (Box 2)
    - Typed loose pages of autobiography, undated; 2 (Box 2)
    - Short stories, undated (Box 2)
- Mark Holloway Papers, undated; Series II; 3; (3 boxes)
  Series II contains Mark Holloway's notes for and drafts of his book on Martha Gordon Crotch.
  - Transcriptions of Crotch diaries, undated; 7 (Box 3)
  - Notes for book, undated; 10 (Box 4)
  - Notes and drafts of book, undated; 15 (Box 5)